Glasses, Glasses, Glasses, Glasses.
（追う男）MEGANE(メガネ) MEGANE
MEGANE MEGANE
Glasses, Glasses, Glasses.
MEGANE MEGANE MEGANE
ひっ はっ ひいい
Glasses, Glasses...
MEGANE MEGANE
MEGANE
Glasses!
Glasses, Glasses, Glasses, Glasses!
MEGANE MEGANE MEGANE
MEGANE MEGANE MEGANE MEGANE
Glasses!
MEGANE MEGANE MEGANE
Nichijou 78
I will now do something that has never been done before and will never be done again.
（フェッちゃん）今までも
そして これからも―
永遠に お目にかかれないこと
やってみようかと思います
エヘッ
Domestic Violence.
ドメスティック バイオレンス
ひゃああ！ ハッ ハッ
What did you think?
どうだった？
（立花(たちばな)みさと･ウェボシー）
“どうだった”って言われてもな
Even if you ask us that...
That was very like you, Fecchan.
（みさと）
フェッちゃんぽかった
That was definitely very like you, Fecchan.
（ウェボシー）ああ 確かに
フェッちゃんぽかった
（みさと）
うん フェッちゃんぽかった
Yeah, that was very like you, Fecchan.
Next I'm going to try something that's not like me.
（フェッちゃん）じゃあ 次は―
私っぽくないことを
やってみようかと思います
ふえーん
I fell!
こけちゃった
That was very like Fecchan.
（みさと･ウェボシー）
フェッちゃんっぽいなあ
Oh.
That's definitely very like Fecchan.
フェッちゃんっぽいなあ
Newcomer 1
Hey! We've got daihuku! How about one?
（男性）はーい 大福ですよ
どうですか？
（中之条(なかのじょう)さん）すまんが―
I'm sorry, but can you wear this instead?
これを着用してもらえんかね
Hey!
（男性）はーい 大福ですよ
We've got daihuku!
How about one?
どうですかあ？
（中之条さん）すまんが―
I'm sorry, but...
しゃべらんでもらえるかね
...could you not talk?
Newcomer 2
Could you possibly put on some clothes?
服を着ることはできんのか？
Are you mad at me?!
すねてるのか？
Newcomer 3
（中之条さん）
なっ！ すねてないのかあ？
You aren't mad at me?
What is it, then?
じゃあ 何なんだ？
Hey...
おいっ
It's all right if you talk right now!
今は しゃべってもいいんだぞ
Love-Like
I hope I pass the test to get into Tokisadame High School.
I hope the person above me passes.
I hope the person to my right passes.
I hope the person below me passes.
Good Luck!
I hope the person to my right passes.
I hope the person below me passes.
Good Luck!
Nichijou 79
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）いきまーす
Here I go!
ハア ハア ハア
ハアッ
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）うーん
（みお）えいっ！
ガアッ！
イエス！
Yes!
You didn't jump it!
跳んでねえよ
え？ いや だって
ちゃんとバーが…
But the bar is-
うん 正確に言おう
To be more precise, you didn't go over it!
超えてねえよ！
Just what should I do for you to properly learn how to jump?
もう 何べん教えたら
ちゃんと跳んでくれんの？
The sun's going down!
日が暮れちゃうよ
（みお）ご… ごめん
次は ちゃんと頑張るから
I'm sorry.
I'll try harder next time.
I'm going to lower the bar this time,
（祐子）今度は
ちょっとバーを落とすから
so just take it slow and jump as I taught you.
ゆっくりでいいから
次は 教えたとおりに跳びなよ
（みお）分かった
I got it.
Anyway, I need to get better before the next examination.
（みお）
とりあえず 次の測定までに
I need to be able to jump, even if it's just a bit.
少しでも跳べるように
ならないと
（みお）よっしゃ！
Or else everyone...
（みお）じゃないとみんなに
...will laugh at me!
笑われちゃうよ
ガアッ！
どうだった！
How was it?!
くうう…
You stupid pumpkin!
この土手カボチャ！
なんで 教えたフォームで
跳ばないのっ
Why don't you jump with the form I taught you?!
Are you messing with me?!
ふざけてんの？
Well, in my head, it's an elegant backward jump...
いやあ 私の中では
キレイな背面跳びなんだけど
An elegant backward jump?
キレイな背面跳び？
Your form is more like...
あんたのフォームは もはや―
...a torpedo!
魚雷だよ
A human... torpedo.
人間 魚雷
I didn't say that!
（祐子）そこまで言ってないよ
いや もう…
Wait...
そこまで いっちゃってるよ
I did say that...
No way! You're joking, right?
いやいやいや まっさかあ
冗談でしょ？
自覚なしか！
You don't even realise it?!
Sorry.
（みお）ごめん
Well, I'll stick around until you can do it, Mio-chan.
まあ みおちゃんが
納得いくまで つきあいますよ
（祐子）いつも
宿題見せてもらってるしね
You always let me copy your homework.
It's my turn today!
今日は私の番ですよ
Let's keep going until you get it!
できるまで気長にやりましょ
Anyway, just take it slow!
とりあえず ゆっくりゆっくり
First, try to jump like you're just stepping over it.
まずは またぐ感じで
跳んでみよっか
Mio-chan, just calm down.
みおちゃん 落ち着いて
大丈夫だよ
It's all right!
katari tsugu hito mo naku
Even if the names of the stars scattered
（みお）運動音痴は
今に始まったことじゃない
This isn't the first time I've been bad at sports.
fuki susabu kaze no naka e
within the fierce winds
Hey, Mio-chan.
（祐子）ちょっと みおちゃん！
これサッカーだから！
This is soccer!
My physical strength is about average.
（みお）
基礎体力は 人並みにある
magire chirabaru hoshi no na wa
and are completely forgotten
But when rules are thrown in, I forget what I'm doing.
だけど そこにルールが絡むと―
とんと 我を忘れちゃう
Sympathetic Heart
Fall!
（師範代）受け身　よーい
wasureraretemo
and not remembered by anyone,
On your mark...
Start!
始めっ！
Mio-chan, falling is the other way around!
みおちゃん逆　受け身が逆だよ
But if I don't do anything about it, nothing will change!
（みお）でも
そこで何もやらなければ
何も変わらない―
Headlight, Taillight   tabi wa mada owaranai
Headlight, Taillight. The journey isn't over yet.
I'll just stay the same!
いつもの私なんだ
Here we go.
（大間々(おおまま)）せーの
…っと　ああ？
Mio-chan, we're not trying to be propellers!
（祐子）
みおちゃん プロペラじゃなくて
逆上がりだよっ！
We're doing somersaults!
（みお）ムダな努力だっていい
I don't care if the effort is wasted.
Headlight, Taillight   tabi wa mada owaranai
Headlight, Taillight. The journey isn't over yet.
I don't care if there are no results!
結果が出なくったっていい
（みお）ハア ハア
ハア ハア
ashiato wa furuame to
Your footsteps vanish into time
However, there is one thing!
（みお）だけど
たった ひとつ
私にもできることがある
There's one thing that I can do for myself!
One, two, three!
（祐子）イチ ニイ サン
furu toki no naka e kiete
along with the falling rain.
ううん アハハ
Let's try once more.
もっかい やっとこっか
I'm doing it for Yukko.
（みお）ゆっこのためにも
tataeru uta wa
Even if songs of praise
I'm going to rest for a while.
ちょっと むこうで休んでくる
Oh, all right.
うん 分かった
eiyuu no tame ni sugitemo
are no longer for heroes,
ハアッ
And I'm doing it for myself!
（みお）私のためにも
Headlight, Taillight   tabi wa mada owaranai
Headlight, Taillight. The journey isn't over yet.
I won't give up!
あきらめない
If I'm going to give up,
あきらめるなら―
I'll give up after I do everything I can!
やるだけやって あきらめてやる
Effort will always open up a door.
（師範代）努力は必ず扉を開く
Headlight, Taillight   tabi wa mada owaranai
Headlight, Taillight. The journey isn't over yet.
（みお）やああ
Headlight, Taillight   tabi wa mada owaranai
Headlight, Taillight. The journey isn't over yet.
このおっ！
Headlight, Taillight   tabi wa mada owaranai
Headlight, Taillight. The journey isn't over yet.
It later became known as the "Torpedo Jump".
White tigers are like this!
They're kinda...
なんか 寝てばっかり
...all sleeping.
That one even has its butt pointed at us.
あの１匹なんか
お尻向けちゃってるよ
I guess.
（みお）そうだね　それに―
Also, they're pretty far away, so we can't see them well.
ずいぶん遠くにいるから
よく見えないし
We came all the way to see this, but it's so boring!
（祐子）せっかく
見にきたのに つまんない
At least we got to see them.
（みお）見れただけでも
よかったじゃん
I guess so.
まあ ねえ
（祐子･みお）
うわ やったあ
Yay!
（阪本(さかもと)）フワア
Nichijou 80
（はかせ）雨だ
It's raining!
I need to bring in the laundry!
洗濯物 入れないと
Hey, where are you going?
（阪本）
おい どこ行くんだよ？
（阪本）フウ
とおっ
わあい
これは もうダメだ
It's too late.
Just bring it in!
（阪本）とにかく入れろ
（東雲(しののめ)なの）ふぃいい
It's raining!
雨だあ
Professor, Sakamoto-san, I'm home!
はかせ 阪本さん
ただいま
It's raining pretty hard outside.
雨スゴかったですね
Did you bring in the laundry?
洗濯物 入れておいて
くれましたか？
It's because Sakamoto told me to bring it in!
だって 阪本が
入れろって言ったから
It's the truth.
ホントだよ
It's really because Sakamoto said that.
ホントに阪本が
入れろって言ったから
Sakamoto-san said to bring it in, so it fell to the ground?
（なの）阪本さんが
入れろって言って―
洗濯物が落ちるんですか？
That's not it.
違うよ  阪本が
入れろって言って―
Sakamoto said to bring it in,
and then he said to drop it.
落とせって言ったから
I didn't say that!
（阪本）言ってねえよ
Geez, that startled me.
ああ ビックリした
What are you saying all of a sudden?!
何 言いだすんだよ ガキは
It's because you said that.
だって言ったじゃん
I never told you to drop it.
（阪本）
落とせとは言ってねえよ
You did.
（はかせ）言った
（阪本）言ってねえよ
I didn't.
You did.
（はかせ）言った
（阪本）言ってねえよ
I didn't.
You did!
（はかせ）言った
（阪本）言ってねえよ
I didn't!
You did!
（はかせ）言った
（阪本）言ってねえって
I didn't!
You did!
（はかせ）言った
（阪本）言ってねえ
I didn't!
もう 勘弁して
Just leave me alone!
Nano.
（はかせ）なの
I'll go sacrifice Sakamoto.
だったら
阪本いけにえにするから―
Is that okay?
いいよね？
What do you mean?
（阪本）どういうことだ？
It's all right.
もう いいです
If you wash the dirt, the clothes will come back to being clean.
汚れは洗濯すれば
元に戻りますから
あっ！ そうか
That's right.
ヘヘヘ そうだったかも
That's right!
However, today won't come back.
でも 今日という日は
戻りませんから
Neither of you are getting any dinner tonight.
２人とも今日の晩ごはんは
抜きにします
Why am I always the victim?
（阪本）クソッ
なんて とばっちりだ
But it was Sakamoto who did it!
だって だって
阪本がやったし―
Which is why I'll go sacrifice him. Is that okay?
阪本いけにえにするから
ねえ いいでしょう
All right.
（なの）分かりました
I'll take Sakamoto-san,
じゃあ 阪本さんをもらって―
and only you won't get dinner.
はかせだけ 晩ごはん抜きです
Wait, no!
違うよ じゃあ
はかせがいけにえになるから
I'll be the sacrifice!
I was the one who dropped them,
だって 落っことしたのは
はかせだし―
ビチョビチョにしたのも
はかせだしって
and I was the one who got them all wet!
あれれ
（なの）じゃーん
Tonight's dinner is omelette rice!
今日の晩ごはんは
オムライスでーす
Eggs were on sale!
卵 安かったんで
Wait, I can eat tonight?
あれ？ はかせ
今日 食べられるの？
あっ！ そうだった
すっかり 忘れてました
Oh right, I completely forgot!
Um, well...
えーと
じゃあ
I'll just let you eat today.
ま… まあ とりあえず
今日は 食べちゃいましょう
やったあ やったあ
Yay!
You won't get anything tomorrow, though!
あした 抜きにしましょう
（はかせ）ヘコ
Swim, swim.
（なの･はかせ）すい すい
Sharky, sharky, chomp!
サメサメ パクン
If that happens, do this!
それなら これなんだ
Mio-chan, Mai-chan!
（祐子）
みおちゃん 麻衣(まい)ちゃん
Selamat pagi!
スラマッパギー
Wasn't it a pain to make a self portrait out of clay?
自画像粘土の宿題
チョーめんどくさくなかった？
（みお）うわ！
その宿題 今日だったっけか？
Oh, that was due today?
What's this?
（祐子）あれれ みお先生
Did Mio-sensei forget to do her homework?
もしかして
お忘れですかにゃあ？
（みお）
くっ てっきり あしただと
I totally thought it was due tomorrow.
Mai-chan, did you do it?
麻衣ちゃん やってきた？
Crap.
（水上(みなかみ)麻衣）しまった
Mai-chan, you, too?
麻衣ちゃんもなんて―
Maybe it'll start raining today.
こりゃひと雨くるかもね
Not just a bit of rain,
ひと雨どころじゃないよ
it's going to be a deluge.
天変地異だよ
A deluge.
天変地異
Nichijou 81
It actually...
（祐子）ホントに
...started raining.
（みお）降ってきた
（和尚(おしょう)）おお お前ら
Y-You guys...
What are you doing to my temple?!
うちの寺に何する気じゃ
ああ この さい銭泥棒が！
You donation thieves!
わああ
あ… 危ねえ
T-That was close!
You're cursed...
たたりじゃあ
Plague bringers!
疫病神じゃあっ
Get out...
出てけ
Get out of my temple!
わしの寺から出ていけ！
"Just go with it"...
（ナレーター）らしくいこう
...is what the girls thought as they were hit by the late autumn rain.
晩秋の雨に打たれながら―
彼女たちは そう思った
（大工健三郎(だいくけんざぶろう)）あっ ああ
Nichijou 82
Please, President!
（桜井 誠(さくらいまこと)）お願いします 部長
I'm going to have a match against Takasaki-sensei.
今から高崎(たかさき)先生と勝負するんで―
Could you be the referee?
審判になってもらって
いいですか？
Referee? For Go Soccer?
審判って 囲碁サッカーの？
That's correct.
（誠）そうです
この勝負に勝てば―
If I win this match, he'll have no choice but to become our advisor.
有無を言わさず
顧問になってもらえるんです
I'm going to win this!
やりますよ 俺
But how do I do it?
でも どうやってやればいいの？
Don't worry.
大丈夫です
The beginner's guide to Go Soccer that I lent you earlier:
前に貸した
「囲碁サッカー入門」
If you take a look at that, you'll be fine.
あれ見ていれば 大丈夫ですよ
It might be my fault for not reading the book,
（大工）入門書を読んでこなかった
俺が悪いんだが
but I have no clue what these two are doing!
この２人
さっきから何やってんだか
全く分かんねえ
Is this really Go Soccer?!
これが 囲碁サッカー？
Even if you had read it, you wouldn't understand.
（小木(おぎ)）入門書を見たって
分かりゃしませんよ
（大工）ああ 小木
Ogi!
Because they both started off with prohibited techniques,
いわば両者
始めから禁じてを使った状態
they're in a high-level stand-off that ignores reason.
セオリー無視の
ハイレベルな攻防です
わあっ！
For example, that arm raised straight up.
例えば
あのまっすぐに伸ばした手
If you consider that a leg on a Go board,
あれが囲碁基盤の
足とするならば―
then the opposition's stance is like the Go stones.
対面(といめん)の あの構えは碁石
It's like they're in perfect unison.
一見 相性は
よさそうに見えますが―
The way he's holding the ball is deceptive.
足に挟んだボールがくせ者
Based on my judgement, these two are...
私の推測ですが この２人
...becoming the sun.
太陽になろうとしている
I have no clue what he's saying!
何 言ってるのか―
さっぱり分かんねえ
（小木）ああ！ 動きます
（大工）ああ
They started moving!
たあっ！
Oh no!
マズい！
Be loved!
ビーラブド
Ogi, what is that supposed-
小木　それは どういう…
Be quiet.
（小木）静かにっ
（大工）へっ？
Don't you get it?
（小木）分かりませんか？
The grave atmosphere around them.
この２人に流れる
したり気な空気
If they make a single mistake,
ヘタしたらこれ―
someone could die.
死人がでますよ
What in the world is going on?
（大工）いったい
何が起こっているんだ
It's been a while since I've seen such a high-level battle!
こんなハイレベルな試合を
見るのは―
私も久しぶりです
Of course, the wind is rustling.
どうりで風が騒ぐわけだ
Oh no!
マズい この構えは―
That stance!
Could he be planning to do that in a field match?!
まさか野良試合でアレをやる気か？
Is he insane?!
正気の沙汰か
くっ しかし この状況
But I can't just stand by and watch in this situation.
見過ごすわけには いかない
Father, I am going to use it.
父上 使わせていただきます
すべては 正義のために―
It's all for the sake of justice!
Shine a light...
光さす 星とならん
...and become a path!
Ogi forbidden style.
小木禁止点流(おぎきんしてんりゅう) 超奥義
Super Ogi!
Ogi Star!
小木星(おぎぼし)
（小木）たあっ！
これぞ あっ ファイナルラブド
This is it!
Oh, Final Loved!
（大工･関口）カア！
（高崎）ハア ハア
Nice going!
やるな
ハア ハア
You too!
先生こそ
Good heavens.
（大工）何てこった
I started this club just to play around.
軽い気持ちで作った
部活だったのだが―
This is...
こりゃあ―
...becoming something outrageous!
大変なことになってきやがった
kakete yuku
駆けてゆく
Endlessly
Word Of The Day
（玉村(たまむら)）ハア
Get down when nobody's looking.
（粘土）踏まれても
踏まれても
Free for
employees
不死鳥のように
よみがえる
それが 俺　粘土
ここに見参
今日も 子どもたちと
戦うべく―
No matter how much I get stepped on, like a phoenix, I shall come back.
さまざまな物に
姿を変えるのだ
次回の「日常」は
第20話
That's me: Clay!
Scramble here!
さあ 子どもたちよ―
Today, I'll be changing into many different forms in order to fight with the kids!
かかってこーい！
Next time on Nichijou: Episode 20.
Narration:    Mitsuya Yuuji
Very well, then! Kids, come at me!